How is he?
كيف حاله؟
I've used acupuncture to regulate his blood and qi.
لقد استخدمت الوخز بالإبر لتنظيم دمه وتشي.
The poison won't reach his heart for the time being.
لن يصل السم قلبه في الوقت الحاضر.
He will wake up in a few days.
سوف يستيقظ في غضون أيام قليلة.
But...
لكن...
But what?
ولكن ماذا؟
Instead of neutralizing this poison, I can only slow the poison's progress.
وبدلاً من تحييد هذا السم، لا أستطيع إلا أن أبطئ تقدم السم.
But I can't do that this time.
ولكن لا أستطيع أن أفعل ذلك هذه المرة.
If we still can't find the antidote,
إذا ما زلنا غير قادرين على العثور على الترياق،
he has a month at best, just 10 days at worst,
له شهر على أفضل تقدير 10 أيام فقط في أسوأ الأحوال،
and I can't save him.
ولا أستطيع إنقاذه.
[REBIRTH]
[ولادة جديدة]
[Episode 25]
[الحلقة 25]
Great Yan has endured months of severe drought this year,
لقد تحمل يان العظيم شهورًا من الجفاف الشديد هذا العام
leaving the autumn harvest poor.
ترك محصول الخريف فقيرا.
Except for the Hongchuan and Pale Tribes, which have surpluses,
باستثناء قبائل هونغتشوان وبالي، التي بها فائض،
other tribes' elders have written to request emergency grain supplies.
وقد كتب شيوخ القبائل الأخرى لطلب إمدادات الحبوب الطارئة.
However...
لكن...
However, the granaries in the Capital of Great Yan
ومع ذلك، مخازن الحبوب في عاصمة يان العظمى
have long been used to supply the military.
منذ فترة طويلة تستخدم لتزويد الجيش.
What about the elder of the Hongchuan Tribe?
ماذا عن شيخ قبيلة هونغتشوان؟
Elder Tubu of the Hongchuan Tribe claimed
شيخ توبو من قبيلة هونغتشوان ادعى
that due to the continuous rain these past few days,
وذلك بسبب الأمطار المستمرة في هذه الأيام القليلة الماضية،
his leg ailment has flared up,
لقد اشتد مرض ساقه،
so he asked for leave to recuperate at home.
فطلب الإجازة للتعافي في المنزل.
Hasn't there been a severe drought for months?
ألم يكن هناك جفاف شديد لعدة أشهر؟
Why?
لماذا؟
Did the Hongchuan Tribe pray for rain?
هل صلت قبيلة هونغتشوان من أجل المطر؟
What about Elder Pale?
ماذا عن الشيخ بالي؟
Did he get rheumatism too?
هل أصيب بالروماتيزم أيضاً؟
Elder Pale went hunting in Mount Hei the day before yesterday.
ذهب الشيخ بالي للصيد في جبل هاي أول من أمس.
It's said he broke his leg because his horse was startled.
ويقال أنه كسر ساقه لأن حصانه قد جفل.
Your Majesty,
صاحب الجلالة،
they are going too far.
إنهم يذهبون بعيدًا جدًا.
They are just unwilling
إنهم فقط غير راغبين
to bring out their surplus grain for emergencies.
لإخراج الحبوب الفائضة لديهم لحالات الطوارئ.
What kind of excuses are those?
أي نوع من الأعذار تلك؟
Your Majesty,
صاحب الجلالة،
we can't blame the elders.
لا يمكننا إلقاء اللوم على الكبار.
In the defeat of Great Yan,
في هزيمة يان العظيم،
every tribe suffered heavy casualties.
عانت كل قبيلة من خسائر فادحة.
Except for the relatively wealthy Hongchuan
باستثناء هونغتشوان الأثرياء نسبيًا
and Pale Tribes,
والقبائل الشاحبة،
the other tribes
القبائل الاخرى
have almost no labor force left
لم يعد هناك أي قوة عمل تقريبًا
for farming.
للزراعة.
Elder Hongchuan and Elder Pale
الشيخ هونغتشوان والشيخ بالي
saw the desolation in the other tribes
رأى الخراب في القبائل الأخرى
and were afraid, so they didn't want to bring out their grain.
وكانوا خائفين، لذلك لم يريدوا لإخراج حبوبهم
Show some mercy.
أظهر بعض الرحمة.
Don't touch me.
لا تلمسني.
Wake up.
استيقظ.
Father.
أب.
Show some mercy.
أظهر بعض الرحمة.
My son!
ابني!
-Mother! -My son!
-الأم! -ابني!
Mother!
الأم!
My son!
ابني!
Come back.
عد.
Mother!
الأم!
Sir, I'm sorry.
سيدي، أنا آسف.
My mother is sick and doesn't recognize anyone.
والدتي مريضة ولا يتعرف على أحد.
Please forgive her.
يرجى أن يغفر لها.
My husband was in the army of Great Yan.
كان زوجي في جيش يان العظيم.
He went to war and didn't come back.
ذهب إلى الحرب ولم يعد.
My mother's lost her mind over the years,
أمي فقدت عقلها على مر السنين،
and she doesn't recognize people anymore.
ولم تعد تتعرف على الناس.
But
لكن
she recognizes the sound of the bell on the horse's reins.
تتعرف على الصوت من الجرس على مقاليد الحصان.
Whenever soldiers pass by,
كلما مر الجنود
she will grab them
سوف تمسك بهم
and call my husband's name.
واتصل باسم زوجي.
My son, you're back.
يا ابني لقد عدت
My son.
ابني.
Sir, please spare us!
سيدي، يرجى تجنيبنا!
My son, you're back.
يا ابني لقد عدت
My son.
ابني.
My son gave me money.
ابني أعطاني المال.
Thank you, Sir.
شكرا لك يا سيدي.
-My son gave me money. -Thank you, Sir.
-ابني أعطاني المال. -شكرا لك يا سيدي.
In the past,
في الماضي
[Capital of Great Yan]
[ عاصمة يان العظمى ]
my father and the Emperor of Great Yong
والدي وامبراطور يونغ العظيم
conquered most of the northeastern plains.
غزت معظم السهول الشمالية الشرقية.
The Emperor of Great Yong designated the area north of Yanming Pass
الإمبراطور العظيم يونغ تم تحديد المنطقة الواقعة شمال ممر يانمينغ
as Great Yan
كما يان العظمى
and gave it to my father.
وأعطاه لأبي.
He said
قال
if the territory of Great Yong was a wolf,
إذا كانت أراضي غريت يونغ ذئباً،
then Great Yan
ثم يان العظمى
would be the wolf's head.
سيكون رأس الذئب.
As long as Great Yan was guarded,
طالما كان يان العظيم تحت الحراسة،
two-thirds of Great Yong's borders would be secure.
ثلثي حدود غريت يونغ سيكون آمنا.
To guard
للحراسة
these two-thirds of the borders,
هذين الثلثين من الحدود،
my father built this city.
والدي بنى هذه المدينة.
The walls of the Capital of Great Yan
أسوار عاصمة يان العظمى
remain impregnable to this day.
وتبقى منيعة حتى يومنا هذا.
It shows the late king's foresight.
ويظهر بعد نظر الملك الراحل.
But now, only the city walls remain strong.
ولكن الآن، فقط أسوار المدينة تبقى قوية.
The entire Great Yan
يان العظيم بأكمله
is already stretched to its limits.
وقد امتدت بالفعل إلى حدودها.
Cheng Yuan,
تشنغ يوان،
I failed to defend Great Yan
لقد فشلت في الدفاع عن يان العظيم
or my father's legacy.
أو تراث والدي.
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
Without you,
بدونك
Great Yan would be long gone.
سوف يختفي يان العظيم منذ فترة طويلة.
Great Yong is a wolf,
عظيم يونغ هو الذئب،
and Biantang is the vast forest
وبيانتانج هي الغابة الشاسعة
surrounding the wolf.
المحيطة بالذئب.
We lost the battle at Longyin Pass.
لقد خسرنا المعركة في ممر لونجين.
If we had won,
لو فزنا
the wolf would've been attacked from both sides
لكان الذئب قد تعرض للهجوم من الجانبين
and become our prey.
وتصبح فريسة لنا.
You did it not just for Queen Chu
أنت لم تفعل ذلك من أجل الملكة تشو فقط
but for Great Yan.
ولكن بالنسبة ليان العظيم.
Others may not understand you,
قد لا يفهمك الآخرون،
but I do.
لكني أفعل.
In the battle against Biantang,
في المعركة ضد بيانتانج
Your Majesty, you only lost Queen Chu,
يا صاحب الجلالة، لقد فقدت فقط الملكة تشو،
but Great Yan and I are still here.
لكن أنا و(يان العظيم) ما زلنا هنا.
Great Yan, you, and I are one.
عظيم يان، أنت وأنا واحد.
Life or death, glory or shame,
الحياة أو الموت، المجد أو العار،
in heaven or hell,
في الجنة أو النار،
always and forever,
دائمًا وأبدًا،
I
أنا
stand with you, Your Majesty.
أقف معك يا صاحب الجلالة.
♪ The sky is so vast ♪
♪ السماء واسعة جداً ♪
♪ The dark clouds are gray ♪
♪ الغيوم الداكنة رمادية ♪
♪ The rain is falling ♪
♪ المطر يتساقط ♪
♪ The eagle is flying ♪
♪ النسر يطير ♪
♪ In the vast wilderness ♪
♪ في البرية الواسعة ♪
♪ The wind blows ♪
♪ تهب الريح ♪
♪ I'm fearless of death ♪
♪ أنا لا أخاف من الموت ♪
♪ And I'll never have regrets ♪
♪ ولن أندم أبدًا ♪
♪ The lonely black eagle ♪
♪ النسر الأسود الوحيد ♪
♪ Is flying against the light ♪
♪ يطير ضد الضوء ♪
♪ Where is my hometown? ♪
♪ أين هو مسقط رأسي؟ ♪
♪ In the vast world ♪
♪ في العالم الواسع ♪
♪ I have no origin ♪
♪ ليس لي أصل ♪
♪ And no destination ♪
♪ ولا وجهة ♪
♪ A pair of stubborn wings ♪
♪ زوج من الأجنحة العنيدة ♪
♪ Is born to fly ♪
♪ ولد ليطير ♪
Don't look.
لا تنظر.
Go home.
اذهب إلى المنزل.
Go, go.
اذهب، اذهب.
Here is your tea.
هنا هو الشاي الخاص بك.
Sorry for the wait.
آسف على الانتظار.
Sir.
سيد.
Who are those corpses
من هي تلك الجثث
hanging on the city gate over there?
معلقة على بوابة المدينة هناك؟
They were slaves from King Ximeng's Palace,
كانوا عبيدا من قصر الملك شيمنغ،
executed by King Ximeng for making mistakes.
أعدمه الملك Ximeng لارتكاب الأخطاء.
I've been here for 3 days.
لقد كنت هنا لمدة 3 أيام.
Every day, different people
كل يوم أشخاص مختلفين
would be hung up here.
سيتم تعليقه هنا.
How many people does King Ximeng kill a day?
كم عدد الأشخاص هل يقتل الملك Ximeng يومًا؟
Keep your voice down, Miss.
اخفضي صوتك يا آنسة
I can see you two are not from Ximeng.
أستطيع أن أرى أنكما لستما من Ximeng.
It's too conspicuous to say such things on the street.
انها واضحة جدا لقول مثل هذه الأشياء في الشارع.
If those Ximeng soldiers hear it,
إذا سمعها جنود Ximeng،
not to mention you two,
ناهيك عنكما،
even I won't survive.
حتى أنا لن أبقى على قيد الحياة.
Are these slaves
هل هؤلاء العبيد
newly presented to King Ximeng?
تم تقديمه حديثًا إلى الملك Ximeng؟
Yes.
نعم.
Go up the mountain out of this gate,
اصعد الجبل من هذه البوابة،
and you'll reach the palace.
وسوف تصل إلى القصر.
Enjoy your tea.
استمتع بالشاي الخاص بك.
I'll see to the other guests.
سأرى الضيوف الآخرين.
Yue Shiyi?
يو شيي؟
Yue Shiyi.
يو شيي.
Why are you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
I went with the Young Master to rescue the Queen of Lingyue.
ذهبت مع السيد الشاب لإنقاذ ملكة Lingyue.
At the agreed place,
في المكان المتفق عليه
he didn't show up.
لم يظهر.
So I returned to the city to find some clues
لذلك عدت إلى المدينة للعثور على بعض القرائن
and happened to meet you.
وحدث أن التقيت بك.
His poison flared up again.
اشتعل سمومه مرة أخرى.
He's recuperating at the Queen of Lingyue's place.
إنه يتعافى في منزل ملكة Lingyue.
He is in no danger for now.
وهو ليس في خطر في الوقت الراهن.
Hurry up.
اسرع.
These have to be sent into the inner palace tonight.
هذه يجب أن ترسل إلى القصر الداخلي الليلة.
We can't delay.
لا يمكننا التأخير.
Hurry up.
اسرع.
Why are these carriages
لماذا هذه العربات
different from the ones we just saw?
مختلفة عن تلك التي رأيناها للتو؟
I asked around among the commoners.
سألت بين عامة الناس.
Under these black cloths
تحت هذه الأقمشة السوداء
are personal female slaves sent into the palace.
هم العبيد الشخصية أرسلت إلى القصر.
Because of their special status, they can't be seen,
بسبب وضعهم الخاص لا يمكن رؤيتهم،
so they are covered with black cloth.
حتى يتم تغطيتها بقطعة قماش سوداء.
I went to scout during the day.
ذهبت لاستكشاف خلال النهار.
King Ximeng's Palace is built against the mountain,
قصر الملك شيمنغ مبني على الجبل
supported by huge rocks.
مدعومة بالصخور الضخمة.
There is an inner palace inside the royal palace.
يوجد قصر داخلي داخل القصر الملكي.
The outer palace is a long stone-stepped corridor.
القصر الخارجي هو ممر طويل متدرج بالحجارة.
The inner palace
القصر الداخلي
is where King Ximeng lives.
هو المكان الذي يعيش فيه الملك Ximeng.
Those carriages covered with black cloth
تلك العربات المغطاة بالقماش الأسود
should be the ones sent to serve in the inner palace.
يجب أن يكونوا هم أرسل للخدمة في القصر الداخلي.
I suppose so.
أعتقد ذلك.
If only those carriages
لو أن تلك العربات
can enter the inner palace,
يمكن أن يدخل القصر الداخلي،
let me go.
دعني أذهب.
I used to be a slave in Zhenhuangcheng.
اعتدت أن أكون عبدًا في Zhenhuangcheng.
I know better than you
أنا أعرف أفضل منك
how not to be exposed.
كيف لا تتعرض.
My Lady,
سيدتي،
you must remember this map clearly.
يجب أن تتذكر هذه الخريطة بوضوح.
There are many mountain paths in the outer palace
هناك العديد من المسارات الجبلية في القصر الخارجي
to escape from.
للهروب من.
But our priority
لكن أولويتنا
is to leave the inner palace first.
هو مغادرة القصر الداخلي أولاً.
We may not be able to enter Ximeng's inner palace,
قد لا نكون قادرين لدخول قصر Ximeng الداخلي
so you must rely on yourself
لذلك يجب أن تعتمد على نفسك
to remember the way to escape.
لتتذكر طريقة الهروب.
The inner palace is enclosed by 8 layers of octagonal palace walls.
القصر الداخلي مغلق بواسطة 8 طبقات من جدران القصر المثمنة.
Every road leads to somewhere, yet also nowhere.
كل طريق يؤدي إلى مكان ما، ولكن أيضًا في أي مكان.
The terrain is complex.
التضاريس معقدة.
You must remember every turning point clearly.
يجب أن تتذكر كل نقطة تحول واضحة.
Once you take the wrong fork,
بمجرد أن تأخذ الشوكة الخاطئة،
it will be extremely difficult to get out.
سيكون الخروج صعبًا للغاية.
After you enter Ximeng's inner palace
بعد دخولك قصر Ximeng الداخلي
and get the antidote,
واحصل على الترياق
you can exit through the south corner gate via the outer palace's mountain path.
يمكنك الخروج من بوابة الزاوية الجنوبية عبر المسار الجبلي للقصر الخارجي.
Minglu and I will wait for you there.
مينجلو وأنا سننتظرك هناك.
I will go with you.
سأذهب معك.
I just went to check on the Young Master.
لقد ذهبت للتو للاطمئنان على السيد الشاب.
He's still in a coma.
وهو لا يزال في غيبوبة.
I can't help much by staying here.
لا يمكنني المساعدة كثيرًا بالبقاء هنا.
I can stay here by myself.
يمكنني البقاء هنا بنفسي.
It's getting late.
لقد فات الوقت.
Let's go.
دعنا نذهب.
Hurry up, hurry up!
أسرع، أسرع!
Before the third watch,
قبل الهزيع الثالث
be sure to send them into the inner palace!
تأكد من إرسالهم إلى القصر الداخلي!
Hurry up, hurry up!
أسرع، أسرع!
Get down!
انزل!
Hurry up!
أسرع!
You wait here.
انتظر هنا.
I'll be right back.
سأعود حالا.
This incense
هذا البخور
smells so good.
رائحة طيبة جدا.
Maybe it's to relax us.
ربما هو للاسترخاء لنا.
My eyes!
عيني!
I can't see anything!
لا أستطيع رؤية أي شيء!
There's something wrong with this incense!
هناك شيء خاطئ مع هذا البخور!
Close your eyes quickly!
أغمض عينيك بسرعة!
My eyes!
عيني!
I can't see anything!
لا أستطيع رؤية أي شيء!
I can't see!
لا أستطيع أن أرى!
My eyes!
عيني!
Quickly cover your eyes with a cloth!
قم بتغطية عينيك بسرعة بقطعة قماش!
Congratulations.
تهانينا.
You will all become King Ximeng's women.
سوف تصبحن جميعاً نساء الملك زيمنغ.
From now on, you'll live in luxury.
من الآن فصاعدا، سوف تعيش في الترف.
You won't need your eyes anymore.
لن تحتاج لعينيك بعد الآن.
The inner palace is enclosed by 8 layers of octagonal palace walls.
القصر الداخلي مغلق بواسطة 8 طبقات من جدران القصر المثمنة.
The terrain is complex.
التضاريس معقدة.
You must remember every turning point clearly.
يجب أن تتذكر كل نقطة تحول واضحة.
Once you take the wrong fork,
بمجرد أن تأخذ الشوكة الخاطئة،
it will be extremely difficult to get out.
سيكون الخروج صعبًا للغاية.
The female slaves selected to enter the inner palace
العبيد الإناث مختارة لدخول القصر الداخلي
will be branded with a plum blossom mark on their arms.
سيتم وصفها بـ علامة زهر البرقوق على أذرعهم.
With this mark,
بهذه العلامة
they will let you in.
سوف يسمحون لك بالدخول.
Keep going.
يستمر في التقدم.
Move forward.
المضي قدما.
Hurry up.
اسرع.
Who are you?
من أنت؟
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
I am a refugee fleeing from Great Yan.
أنا لاجئ هارب من يان العظمى.
My parents have both died.
لقد مات والداي.
I had to wander to Ximeng to survive.
اضطررت للتجول في Ximeng من أجل البقاء.
A refugee.
لاجئ.
Then why are there blade scars on your back?
ثم لماذا هناك ندوب شفرة على ظهرك؟
I encountered robbers on the way.
لقد واجهت لصوصًا في الطريق.
I was seriously injured
لقد أصبت بجراح خطيرة
and tried my best to escape here,
وحاولت قصارى جهدي للهروب هنا،
just to survive.
فقط من أجل البقاء.
I came to serve you voluntarily.
جئت لخدمتك طوعا.
I'm willing to serve you.
أنا على استعداد لخدمتك.
As long as I can live and get to eat,
طالما أستطيع أن أعيش وأحصل على الطعام،
I'll always stay by your side.
سأبقى دائما بجانبك.
Come here.
تعال الى هنا.
You held weapons before?
هل حملت أسلحة من قبل؟
Who are you?
من أنت؟
Where is the antidote to Blood on Snow?
أين الترياق لدماء على الثلج؟
Tell me, or I will kill you.
أخبرني، وإلا سأقتلك.
You are the real King Ximeng.
أنت الملك الحقيقي Ximeng.
Hurry!
عجل!
Oh no. They are Ximeng soldiers.
أوه لا. إنهم جنود Ximeng.
Go!
يذهب!
This way!
من هنا!
This way! Chase them!
من هنا! مطاردتهم!
Hurry!
عجل!
Stop! Chase them!
قف! مطاردتهم!
Stop!
قف!
-We are exposed! Hurry! -Don't run!
-نحن مكشوفون! عجل! -لا تهرب!
-This way! -Run! Run!
-من هنا! -يجري! يجري!
Stop!
قف!
Don't run!
لا تركض!
I know who you are.
أنا أعرف من أنت.
Seven years ago,
منذ سبع سنوات،
an escaped slave of Great Yong
عبد هارب من غريت يونغ
raised an army in Zhenhuangcheng with the Heir Apparent of Great Yan,
قام بتكوين جيش في Zhenhuangcheng مع ولي العهد يان العظيم،
catching the late emperor of Great Yong off guard.
القبض على الإمبراطور الراحل غريت يونغ على حين غرة.
I respect you for your courage.
أنا أحترمك على شجاعتك.
When Zhuge Yue's body is brought back later,
عندما جثة تشو قه يو يتم إعادته لاحقًا،
I will let you die together.
سأترككما تموتان معًا.
You betrayed us.
لقد خنتنا.
What are you going to do to Zhuge Yue?
ماذا ستفعل بـ Zhuge Yue؟
To save you, Zhuge Yue
لإنقاذك، تشو قه يو
traded his life with me.
لقد تاجر بحياته معي
He broke his promise first
لقد أخلف وعده أولا
and refused to be my slave.
ورفض أن يكون عبدي.
Even if I don't kill him,
ولو لم أقتله،
he won't live much longer.
لن يعيش لفترة أطول.
I don't want to kill you.
أنا لا أريد أن أقتلك.
Don't force my hand.
لا تجبر يدي.
The Emperor of Great Yong is incompetent.
الإمبراطور يونغ العظيم غير كفء.
A mere female slave
مجرد جارية
has turned Great Yong and Great Yan upside down.
لقد تحول إلى Great Yong ويان العظيم رأسا على عقب.
I heard you also abolished slavery in Biantang.
سمعت أنك ألغيت العبودية أيضًا في بيانتانج.
Let me tell you,
دعني أخبرك،
slaves are the most lowly and inferior animals.
العبيد هم الأكثر تواضعا والحيوانات الدنيا .
They barely have enough to eat or wear
بالكاد يجدون ما يكفيهم من طعام أو لبس
and are barely considered human!
وبالكاد يعتبرون بشرًا!
And you still vainly hope to save them?
وما زلت تأمل عبثًا في إنقاذهم؟
Fine.
بخير.
Then I will let you know
ثم سأخبرك
what a slave really is.
ما هو العبد حقا.
Throw her into the slave pen.
رميها في قلم الرقيق.
Let her and her companions
دعوها وصحبها
get along well.
تعايش جيدًا.
Xing.
شينغ.
Xiao Ran.
شياو ران.
Where is Xing?
أين هو شينغ؟
Is Xing here too?
هل شينغ هنا أيضاً؟
Lie down and don't move.
استلقِ ولا تتحرك.
I am applying acupuncture needles.
أنا أطبق إبر الوخز بالإبر.
These needles can temporarily suppress the heat poison in your body,
يمكن استخدام هذه الإبر بشكل مؤقت قمع السم الحراري في جسمك،
so you can live a few more days until you get the antidote.
حتى تتمكن من العيش بضعة أيام أخرى حتى تحصل على الترياق.
Xing.
شينغ.
I will go outside to brew your medicine.
سأذهب للخارج لتحضير الدواء الخاص بك.
Lie quietly and don't move around.
استلقِ بهدوء ولا تتحرك.
There is some noise outside.
هناك بعض الضوضاء في الخارج.
General Chu has gone to King Ximeng's Palace for your antidote.
لقد ذهب الجنرال تشو إلى قصر الملك Ximeng للترياق الخاص بك.
I fear she's in trouble.
أخشى أنها في ورطة.
No one is in the room!
لا أحد في الغرفة!
They should be nearby.
ينبغي أن يكونوا في مكان قريب.
Keep searching!
استمر في البحث!
The sheep has fallen into the trap.
لقد وقع الخروف في الفخ.
Why haven't you acted yet?
لماذا لم تتصرف بعد؟
Is your aim true?
هل هدفك صحيح؟
That's the castor powder I spent a long time developing.
هذا هو مسحوق الخروع لقد قضيت وقتًا طويلاً في التطوير.
Don't waste it.
لا تضيعوه.
There's no one here.
لا يوجد أحد هنا.
-No one's here.
-لا أحد هنا.
Your Majesty,
صاحب الجلالة،
I've failed to kill Zhuge Yue.
لقد فشلت في قتل Zhuge Yue.
My sins are grave.
خطاياي خطيرة.
Please punish me, Your Majesty.
من فضلك عاقبني يا صاحب الجلالة.
As long as you kill Zhuge Yue,
طالما أنك تقتل Zhuge Yue،
I'll give you the antidote to Blood on Snow.
سأعطيك الترياق إلى الدم على الثلج.
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
I can give you the antidote,
أستطيع أن أعطيك الترياق،
but you must take your crazy man and leave,
ولكن يجب أن تأخذ يا رجلك المجنون وارحل
the further the better.
وكلما كان ذلك أفضل.
From now on, there will be no Lingyue Clan in Ximeng.
من الآن فصاعدا، لن تكون هناك عشيرة لينغيو في زيمنغ.
As long as they obediently become Ximeng people
ما داموا مطيعين أصبحوا شعب Ximeng
and submit to me,
وأسلمني
I will spare their lives.
سوف أنقذ حياتهم.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
شكرا لك يا صاحب الجلالة.
By the way,
بالمناسبة
I have a gift for you.
لدي هدية لك.
Follow me.
اتبعني.
Alright.
على ما يرام.
Baze!
بايز!
There's one thing I've never figured out.
هناك شيء واحد لم أكتشفه أبدًا.
You said earlier that in Biantang,
قلت في وقت سابق أنه في بيانتانغ،
you accidentally let Zhuge Yue escape,
لقد سمحت لـ Zhuge Yue بالهروب عن طريق الخطأ،
and that you lied out of fear of me.
وأنك كذبت خوفا مني.
Since he knew you wanted to kill him,
منذ أن عرف أنك تريد قتله،
why would he travel thousands of miles
لماذا يسافر آلاف الأميال
from Biantang to save you?
من Biantang لإنقاذك؟
So I summoned Baze to ask.
لذا استدعيت باز لأسأله.
I didn't expect him
لم أتوقعه
to be so loyal to you.
أن أكون مخلصًا جدًا لك.
No matter how I tortured him,
مهما عذبته
he insisted that he released Zhuge Yue
أصر على إطلاق سراح Zhuge Yue
and privately went to send him a message,
وذهبت على انفراد لأرسل له رسالة
asking him to come and save you,
تطلب منه أن يأتي ويخلصك،
while you knew nothing about it.
بينما كنت لا تعرف شيئا عن ذلك.
He's such a loyal subordinate.
إنه مثل هذا المرؤوس المخلص.
I think you must like him very much,
أعتقد أنك تحبه كثيرًا،
so I spared his life,
فأنقذت حياته،
as a reward for you.
كمكافأة لك.
Remember,
تذكر
there won't be him alone.
لن يكون هناك وحده.
If it happens again,
إذا حدث ذلك مرة أخرى،
you will receive
سوف تتلقى
more rewards.
المزيد من المكافآت.
Whoever kills her
من يقتلها
can have 2 steamed buns tonight.
يمكن أن تتناول 2 كعك مطهو على البخار الليلة.
-Don't run! -Stop!
-لا تهرب! -قف!
Go.
يذهب.
Report!
تقرير!
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
General Meng En has brought back Zhuge Yue from Great Yong.
لقد أعاد الجنرال منغ إن تشو قه يو من غريت يونغ.
You mean
تقصد
he has brought Zhuge Yue back alive?
لقد أعاد Zhuge Yue إلى الحياة؟
Exactly.
بالضبط.
Go wait in the main hall.
اذهب وانتظر في القاعة الرئيسية.
Summon the Queen of Lingyue.
قم باستدعاء ملكة Lingyue.
Yes.
نعم.
Eat.
يأكل.
Greetings, Your Majesty.
تحياتي يا صاحب الجلالة.
Zhuge Yue.
تشوغي يو.
Didn't I tell you to kill him?
ألم أخبرك أن تقتله؟
Forgive me, Your Majesty.
اغفر لي يا صاحب الجلالة.
I couldn't kill him.
لم أستطع قتله.
You've been poisoned by my castor powder.
لقد تم تسميمك بواسطة مسحوق الخروع الخاص بي.
You'll soon bleed from your 7 orifices and die.
سوف تنزف قريبا من فتحاتك السبعة وتموت.
Don't move if you want the antidote.
لا تتحرك إذا كنت تريد الترياق.
Where is Chu Qiao?
أين تشو تشياو؟
Someone, kill him!
شخص ما، قتله!
Quick, gouge out his eyes!
بسرعة، اقتلعوا عينيه!
Stop hiding your handsome face,
توقف عن إخفاء وجهك الوسيم،
Su Gulin.
سو جولين.
What did you say?
ماذا قلت؟
It's you, isn't it,
إنه أنت، أليس كذلك،
Su Gulin?
سو جولين؟
Shut up!
اسكت!
When I was in Great Yong,
عندما كنت في غريت يونغ،
I heard a story.
سمعت قصة.
Thirty years ago,
منذ ثلاثين عاما،
there was a slave in Ximeng,
كان هناك عبد في Ximeng،
named
اسمه
Su Gulin.
سو جولين.
He united with some other slaves
واتحد مع بعض العبيد الآخرين
to resist the oppression of the slave owners in Ximeng,
لمقاومة القمع من أصحاب العبيد في Ximeng،
but was betrayed by his fellow slaves.
ولكن تعرض للخيانة من قبل زملائه العبيد.
The slave owners in Ximeng
أصحاب العبيد في Ximeng
gave him the cruelest punishment of branding his face,
وأعطاه أقسى عقوبة من وسم وجهه
branding the word "slave" on his face.
وسم كلمة "عبد" على وجهه.
Everyone thought
الكل فكر
that Su Gulin died from the branding punishment,
أن سو جولين مات من عقوبة الوسم،
but no one knew how he managed to survive.
لكن لم يعرف أحد كيف تمكن من البقاء على قيد الحياة.
Later, he returned to this land
ثم عاد إلى هذه الأرض
and punished evil with evil,
وعاقب السيئة بالسيئة
and instead became the biggest slave owner in Ximeng,
وأصبح بدلا من ذلك أكبر مالك للعبيد في Ximeng،
Su Gulin.
سو جولين.
You are...
أنت...
from the Zhuge family.
من عائلة Zhuge.
The Zhuge family
عائلة تشوغي
is the biggest slave owner
هو أكبر مالك للعبيد
that keeps slaves for the Emperor of Great Yong.
الذي يبقي العبيد للإمبراطور العظيم يونغ.
I think you must know better than I do
أعتقد أنك يجب أن تعرف أفضل مني
that all these slaves
أن كل هؤلاء العبيد
are stupid and despicable.
هم أغبياء وحقير.
You should stand by my side.
يجب أن تقف بجانبي.
Why do you want to save a female slave?
لماذا تريد إنقاذ جارية؟
I'll ask you again,
سأسألك مرة أخرى،
where exactly is Chu Qiao?
أين هو بالضبط تشو تشياو؟
You are late.
لقد تأخرت.
She has been
لقد كانت
torn apart
ممزقة
and eaten by her kind.
ويأكلها نوعها.
Kill him! Don't mind me!
اقتله! لا مانع لي!
No one will leave here alive tonight!
لن يغادر أحد هنا على قيد الحياة الليلة!
I don't want to hurt you.
أنا لا أريد أن يؤذيك.
I have no choice.
ليس لدي خيار.
You...
أنت...
You and your clan don't want to live anymore?
أنت وعشيرتك لا تريد أن تعيش بعد الآن؟
I want to kill you
أريد أن أقتلك
just so my clan can live on.
فقط حتى تتمكن عشيرتي من العيش.
Baze is already dead.
باز ميت بالفعل.
Baze,
باز،
I'm sorry.
أنا آسف.
I won't let you die in vain.
لن أتركك تموت عبثاً
I won't be threatened by you anymore.
لن أتعرض للتهديد من قبلك بعد الآن.
All this
كل هذا
is over!
انتهى!
Kill me,
اقتلني،
and you'll never get the antidote for Blood on Snow.
ولن تحصل أبدا الترياق للدم على الثلج.
The King of Lingyue will die.
سوف يموت ملك Lingyue.
Zhuge Yue will also die.
سوف يموت Zhuge Yue أيضًا.
You will die too!
سوف تموت أيضا!
How are you?
كيف حالك؟
Zhuge Yue,
تشوغي يو،
I-I don't owe you anymore.
أنا - أنا لا أدين لك بعد الآن.
Lingyue.
لينغيو.
Chu Qiao...
تشو تشياو...
is...
هو...
in the slave pen.
في قلم العبد .
Go save her quickly.
اذهب وانقذها بسرعة
I don't want to owe her either.
لا أريد أن أدين لها أيضًا.
I'll leave my clan
سأترك عشيرتي
to you to protect.
لك للحماية.
I promise you.
أعدك.
Zhuge Yue,
تشوغي يو،
can you hug me?
هل تستطيع أن تعانقني؟
You will all
سوف جميعا
be buried with me.
تدفن معي.
Everyone retreat outside the inner palace!
الجميع يتراجع خارج القصر الداخلي!
Kill trespassers!
قتل المتسللين!
Xing.
شينغ.
I'm afraid this time,
أخشى هذه المرة،
life and death will truly do us apart.
الحياة والموت سيفرقاننا حقًا.
Huan Huan.
هوان هوان.
I've lost Great Yan.
لقد فقدت يان العظيم.
Can you help me get it back?
هل يمكنك مساعدتي في استعادتها؟
The fastest way to cool him down
أسرع طريقة لتبريده
is to immerse his whole body in ice water.
هو غمر جسده كله في الماء المثلج.
You've always been protecting me.
لقد كنت دائما تحميني.
Now,
الآن،
it's my turn to protect you.
حان دوري لحمايتك.